so this is samuta nikaya 7.2
and on one occasion a Brahman heard that
another Brahman had gone forth from the
home life into homelessness in the
presence of the blessed one so he he
sort of changed his religion and this
Brahman anger angered and displeased
went to the blessed one and on arrival
insulted him with rude and harsh words
so he was telling the Buddha off and
then the Buddha says
what do you think Brahman
do friends or relative relatives come to
you as guests
he says yes they occasionally do that
and do you serve them with food and
drinks so yes
and if they don't accept those offerings
to whom do those offerings belong
if they don't accept them the offerings
still belong to me
and the Buddha says likewise Brahman we
who do not abuse anyone who do not scold
anyone who do not quarrel against anyone
refuse to accept from you the abuse the
scolding and the quarrel that you let
loose at us
it still belongs to you
Brahman one who abuses his abuser who scolds the
one who abuses his abuser who scolds the
one who scolds him who fights against
the one who fights with him
he is said to partake of the meal
to enter upon an exchange but we not we
do not partake of your meal we do not
enter upon an exchange it still belongs
to you
and the brahmana says
well like oh you know
like oh you know
the king together with his consort know
this of the master Gautama Gautama is
the contempt kotama is an arrow hunt and
yet master Gautama gets angry
so he's like oh yeah
and the Buddha replies how can anger
arise in one who's angerless in the
tamed one of righteous living in one
liberated by Perfect knowledge
in the stable one who abides in peace
one who repays an angry man with anger
thereby makes things worse for himself
not repaying an angry man with anger one
wins a battle hard to win
he practices for the welfare of both his
own and the others when knowing that his
assailant is angry he remembers to
maintain his peace when he achieves the
cure for both his own and the others
those unskilled and Dumber consider him
a fool
so it is a question a few questions that
I gathered from from this
that others seem to be interested in
because whenever I meet a certain rude
person I wish they meta
I wish they meta
but as much as I have done this that
person Still Remains rude
why is the power of meta not working
how would you answer that
this is not matter what they're putting
okay that's correct and any other way
any one
one
yeah exactly yeah math is not working
because that's not what Matt is supposed
to work
what was that
uh friendliness is your framework of
your mind it's your attitude it's your
cultivation in face
in face
of rudeness and so on
and the whole point of praximata is so
that you
don't give rise to anger or your will
doesn't matter how long the external
um
abuse rudeness and so on lasts it's not
that's not the problem
it sounds to me like this person's using
meta as a retaliation you know wait no
it's you're using meta as a way out of
the unpleasant experience uh do matters
so they'll stop being angry so we're all
friends again
why well because I dislike the
discomfort of experiencing rudeness
which means I'm moved by it I'm pressure
by it I'm not at peace internally when I
experience those things
so matter should shelter me from those
things no matter should make you
immovable in regard to those things
that's it
what it means like someone is having
thoughts of kindness or trying to spread
meta energy to the person but that that
whole attitude is one of
trying to like attack or retaliate
against that rudeness rather than yeah
exactly yeah true it's acting out yeah
it's partaking that meal just in a
different way yeah but you're still
doing it because you're experiencing the
unpleasantness of rudeness
another kind of question that somebody
might I might ask is like
if I'm doing meta properly
this I shouldn't be
it shouldn't even be uncomfortable it
shouldn't be unpleasant for somebody to
insult me or something I should just
care at all
is that the case
or can it still be like because you said
um you don't you don't want the
discomfort of the anger that's why you
act out because somebody might say oh
but if I was doing it rice
it shouldn't be uncomfortable at all
it's not because I don't want right
right right right right
not at all no the abusive words will
remain abusive words so you need to be
like heat cold
rain wind abusive words so it's going to
be uncomfortable but none of that
discomfort can move the mind or can make the Mind
can move the mind or can make the Mind
re-engage willingly with ill will
so it will remaining perturbable
so just because the Buddha doesn't get
angry in this case doesn't mean it was
like he's unaware of the of the actions
of that that brahmana that he was rude
and offensive no no of course
if somebody comes in this room and I'm
showering them with attitude of
friendliness is that spreading of matter no what is
is that spreading of matter no what is
that then
um what is the showering then like like
I'm sort of welcoming doing all these
things just to make them feel my
friendship well it's it's acting out of
craving for so so
um so then when the Buddha says he
uh
spreads meta pervades pervades the
entire world with it
pervades all the quarters with it
is that not the same
pervading the world
pervading the individuals so it is
providing the groups
um
like a negative
so it's pervading and spreading would I
refer to say the same or different
uh different
so what is pervading then
how is providing different from
spreading like um colloquially and
like um colloquially and
um no practically yeah so say we
describe spreading of matter showing a
friendliness and engaging with it by
thinking positive thoughts all that
so what is pervading then if it's
different than that
how would you do pervading
how would you pervade the world
with your attitude of friendliness
where is that done
internally yeah it's not done in the
world that you assume of others
pervading the the quotas it's all done
internally and it requires no acting out
it requires no overly showing these
attitudes which are all rooted exactly in craving
which are all rooted exactly in craving
and wanting other person to be affected
by your friendliness and that's not
mathematics on the level of the Mind
so the up down
east west in every direction do you have
to travel physically to snow you already
are doing it internally he just gets
conflated that type of pervading gets
conflated with all these external acts
oh see this is what it's meant by that
so it's like I'm pervading I'm
visualizing and then I'm expressing it
to everyone everything all the time
and that's completely not what matters
because the same attitude of pervading
uh you know you cultivate for all four
Brahma viharas yeah exactly so how are
you going to express your difference
yeah Equanimity how are you gonna pervey
that onto the others spread them yeah
spread equanimity
like well that's not going to be
inspired that's not spreadable yeah
exactly but it is you can pervade it
yeah you can pervade all quarters in
your mind in all directions as far as
your thought goes with that attitude
so it's a completely and internal
practice which is why exactly it will
establish you in the dwelling of brahmas
no matter what anyone does no matter if
you don't do anything externally you
just sit silently
of course if you spread such attitude
internally not externally if you pervade
all the quarters within that attitude
then it doesn't matter what comes to
your senses or who comes through senses
that attitude will not be able to be
perturbed and that's how you've
successfully come through the meta when
you are not perturbed by things they
would want to perturb you with your will
and so on
and he has absolutely nothing to do with
other person in persons at all otherwise
it's conditional on yeah their actions
yeah we said that before in those other
talks like you know so
when that uh when the Buddha says and
then you protect that State of Mind as a
mother would protect the child no not
protect random people that's not the
problem mind the real will is your
problem being the perturbed away from
the wholesome State of Mind of
friendliness is your problem so that's
where you stay
guarding that
to another question
is I hear many people voicing their
wrong views
and I don't like the fact that they are
spreading such misguided information
but when I try to point out their faulty
understandings from a place of Good Will
and compassion I'm usually met with
hostility should I just let others promote
should I just let others promote
unbeneficial things or should I actively
try to help them despite their hostility
if I don't say something am I not then
complicit in their wrong views to some
degree am I not complicit in here can you
am I not complicit in here can you
partake in other people's actions in
other people's internal choices are
beings owners of their own actions or
they own a bit of their own actions
better than someone else's actions
so it's not a problem none of that can
be a problem you are making it a problem
by not being able to tolerate it
by not being able to not take it out of
it
so you act out of your own craving
because other people hold all these
wrong views rooted in craving
so you got your answer there in a way
you could nearly just I mean you happen
to hear other people or see other people
doing some things that you find
misguided or that you disagree with
but assuming the duty to be to be to
correct yeah but now if you kind of can
take that to its conclusion well you're
just going to have to endless like you
spend your entire life certainly because
vast majority will always remain in
darkness will always remain with wrong
views we'll always remain very
misrepresenting the things so
Enlightenment is not about correcting
everybody else just about fixing your
own issue and that's how you practice
for both
but that's a hard thing for to accept
for somebody who's still doesn't want to
relinquish their own righteous craving
when you say practices for both by
becoming enlightened himself no no but
no you must be more engaged with the
world you must bring social change you
must affect how you must you must
correct them
actually no you don't you can if you
want to but you better be aware of the
reasons why you're doing it because it
might well be the same reasons that
these people have because of which they
are in such Darkness craving and desire
righteousness and blindness
so
householders lay people and one of them
after a certain amount of time says okay
I have to go now and he leaves and then
the Buddha says
you know if he had stayed a bit longer
he would have seen the Dharma and
attained world view
but he didn't say anything like it
wasn't his yeah yeah he didn't even say
it and when the guy was right in front
of him maybe he should stay a bit longer
it was up to him to go
so this is a kind of similar question is
I sometimes get annoyed by how others
speak to me and feel that they should at
least learn how to address address
others correctly so that the world in
general is a better place I tried to
wish them well but deep down I'm still
annoyed and despite my well wishes when
I engage with the person my annoyance is
what shows itself and of my good
intentions because that's the main
reason for the right direction so so
what should I do to better prepare
myself for the next time someone says
something annoying
well give up the idea of world becoming
a better place to begin with
because why is why is the world not a
better place is it because people
speak bad things yeah okay why do people
speak bad things why do people do bad
things why do people kill
why do people lie why do people steal
cheat gain at the expense of others
gain at the expense of others
enslave others and all the other
Misfortune in the world why do they do
that
yeah because of Desire because of
central desire that's it
so you want to fix the world that's
where you fix it you don't fix it by
just making everybody comply to your
worldview even if it's a right worldview
it's not going to work because things
you're making them comply with were
never the problem they were the result
of the problem of desire and that's what
really said when
Sons fight with fathers mothers with
fathers husbands and daughters and and
Kings with other kings and everybody the
whole world fights because of central
desire because of desires that's it the
hate for pain well that all comes with
it but basically for as long as you're
acting out of your desires the world
will be the way the world is so you want
to make a world a better place
start uprooting the desire
wait where do you start at in others or
in yourself well again you don't really
need to answer that question so
you will be factually making a world a
better place if you free yourself from
Central desire means there is one being
less in this world messy world
fuel we desire where there is one person
less that has that desire
that has that desire
one desired has been extinguished so
that is factually an improvement
so one step at a time and then teach
others how to do the same
but then by then you would have
recognized where the problem is so the
problem is not the state of the world
that's just the result of the problem
which is the design so for as long as
you're acting out of the same desires
even righteously you're still adding the
same fuel to the same world to the same
problem of it
right that view said that that the world
will be a
get to a stage where it's just a
wonderful place a peaceful place
everyone's happy that's just your desire
again yeah
and somebody else will come I don't want
to well I like the world the way it is
that's my design so what do we do now
while we fight
sooner or later it will have to lead to
that and then the other one wins if you
end up fighting him
well whoever wins means anyway you you
you made the world a better place by
fighting in violence which is always
what people resort to eventually even
the most well-wishing you know I think
making world a better place well nothing
seems to work let's just resort to force
it's actually quite a useful
contemplation in a way because
um
you know you can see the things that
people do to each other
um on a very
Grand scale like all kinds of corruption
Avery whatever like that like you can look at
whatever like that like you can look at
it and be disgusted by it it's very
obvious
but when you if you see if you realize
oh like what's the cause of this this
person is you know their actions happen
to have these Grand repercussions on a
huge scale that affect thousands of
people because they're in a position of
power or something or it's exactly the
same thing that's
drives me that makes me act towards
something I want or tried to get away or
try to deal with something I dislike and
like even that discussed with the world
can kind of make you oh like I should
restrain this because it's the same
thing yeah that person probably felt the
same discussed which is why he decided
to conquer this whole culture and
destroy it and so on
so you're just acting under the same
reasons completely
um covering it up
covering up the root of the problem
doing the same thing as that Suitor says
you're partaking in exchange you're both
doing the same thing oh he started it
doesn't matter
from your point of view you are the one
starting it for yourself he can't start
it for you
no matter abuse can start abuse
can start it can make you an abuser only
your actions can then
take you in that direction
nobody can make and make you get angry
exactly
and certainly nobody can make you act
out of that anger further
this is frozen you know as long as
somebody thinks oh he's talking he
abused me he revealed me if you do not
give up those thoughts
you will not be able to abandon ill will
yeah something along those lines yeah
in the quarrels in the world will never
end yeah this is it The Suitor of the
acrobats 47.19
the blessed one said once a bamboo
acrobat having erected a bamboo pole
addressed his assistant come climb up
the ball the bamboo pull and stand on my
shoulders as you say master the assistant answered
as you say master the assistant answered
and climbing the bamboo pole stood on
his shoulders
bend the bamboo acrobat said to his
assistant now you watch after me and
I'll watch after you thus protecting
each other watching after each other
will show off our skill receive our
reward and come down safely from the
bamboo Pole
when he had said this the assistant the
assistant said to him but that won't do
at all master you watch after yourself
and I'll watch after myself and thus
with each of us protecting ourselves
watching after ourselves we'll show off
our skill receive our reward and come
down safely
and they would say what the assistant
said to to her master was the right way
in that case
monks for the safeguarding of oneself
Sati patana should be practiced
for the safeguarding of others Sati
patana should be practiced
when safeguarding yourself you Safeguard
others when safeguarding others you Safeguard
when safeguarding others you Safeguard
yourself
why is that yeah and how yeah it does it
explains it but no I won't talk about it
I don't just announce it when
safeguarding yourself you Safeguard
others yes so why by safeguarding
yourself with mindfulness you are automatically
with mindfulness you are automatically
safeguarding others
our others not safe
by my acting out a little bit by
anyone's acting out of your will agree
the version of delusion actually so
that is always
there cannot be no there cannot be any
other route of that non-safety of others
so if everybody would actually
just guard themselves
there would be no quarreling there will
be no violence there will be no abuse
and others would be automatically the
result of that would be safety of others
so if if the root of every every abuse
every violence every kind of suffering
inflicted upon others is Guided by
everybody individually
that's it the world factually becomes a
better place because there are no more
expressions of anger you will hatred
and so on and Desires in that sense as
well responsible
responsible
yeah but it's just factually it's like
it's not even kind of oh yeah we got
ourselves in the world no factually when
others are not safe is because somebody
is acting against that and those acts
can only be rooted in greed aversion or
distraction if you guard yourself
against those you cannot possibly come
near those acts they would endanger
others so effectually the world would be a
so effectually the world would be a
safer place
so let us just practically start for the
average killing precepts yeah exactly not
killing precepts yeah exactly not
killing
killing cheating not harming a lying
that actually says that like by
observing these uh punch Stiller yeah
one gives immeasurable safety to the
world yeah
others can trust that that you won't
kill them or even if they don't trust
Factory to the extent that you're guiding
to the extent that you're guiding
yourself to that extent there is no
expression of of unwholesome towards
others so Factory the world is a better place
so Factory the world is a better place
to that degree
you say if you
if you bodily Behavior your verbal
Behavior a person can still be quite can
still be give rise to that unwholesome
intentions who that person yeah yeah like and
who that person yeah yeah like and
wholesome intentions but
her wholesome intention is not a danger
to others
acting out of unwholesome intentions is
so if you if your sealer is unbroken if
that's where your effort is if you
restrain your senses even if you have
the most Cruel Intentions in your mind
you're not acting out of them but if now
I'm cultivating those cool intentions I
don't harm anyone well then you won't
have internal peace but you are still
factually uh not contributing towards
the suffering of the world because
you're not acting out of it
but yeah eventually well depends like
we're not talking about necessary
practice for our country we're talking
about making a world a better place
but yeah if you want to be completely at
peace unable to even have such
intentions then yeah but even for that
you still need to restrain yourself
first so whether you have such intentions or
so whether you have such intentions or
not the work that needs to be done
beforehand remains unchanged
because if your intentions are
clean your mind is restraint in that
sense then there is absolutely no
possibility of acting out yes but in
order for your intention to be clean am
I restrained you need to have thoroughly
not acted out for a long time yeah and
that will and also it won't be possible
to be honest it won't be possible
theoretically you could see how you
could still have thoughts available in
cruelty arising if you have been
thoroughly restrained and withdrawn from
unwholesome for a you know long period
of time mind will have to calm down
so those thoughts will be setting you
were coming up because there was still
an opportunity I hope
that you might give rise to expressing
them but once you haven't been giving rise
but once you haven't been giving rise
those thoughts will come down
so yeah still the same work same
practice
and a question in regards to The Suitor
says this attitude of the master acrobat
seems like the correct one
otherwise he wouldn't be the master
so you know I'll look at you
so selfishness does does result in harm
to others
and if we can just be unselfish and help
others putting ourselves second then the
society would be a better place and we
would get rid of conceit which is
basically anata is this not also a valid
path to nibana a number of
contradictions there first of all
selfishness is not the reason
selfishness is the result also you are
selfish because of the desires
because of craving
so your selfishness is not the root of
all the problem so you just need to put
yourself second no where do you first or
second you're selfish because you're
doing it because you have a desire to do
so I would desire to be second well she
has a desire to be second so now we're
going to quota
you have the same desire but yeah who's
the most humble wealth exactly one of
them can only be one of us can be second
we can both be the same
so that's the point that's not the root
of the problem
selfishness through to the problem put
myself second the world is fixed see we
all just put ourselves second
well then what and we're all first again
we're all acting out of our desires to
be second but not desire is the root of
the problem
craving is the root of the problem
to the next out of that and then yeah
but I still as I said things will then
become clear if you start practicing
like this you realize yeah this is how
factually the world is becomes a better
place but the world will never become a
better place
on the level of the world because people
are not the same they're not born with
the same faculty it's not born with the
same intent like like state of mind so
to speak
and some people just will never ever be
able to understand these things or
accept them or restrain themselves
so factually majority of the world will
always remain in darkness that's just
the nature of it much like the animal
around
but to that extent you recognize even if
so
if I remove desire in the in this
creature and maybe if somebody asked me I can
and maybe if somebody asked me I can
teach them if not well that's still not
my problem but just to the extent of
fixing myself fixing design and craving
here the world is brighter to that
extent and that is the most direct the most
and that is the most direct the most
verifiable influencing of the world
this is Sati patana should be practiced
dear God yourself
so you're seeing things in the correct
order Yeah well yeah the right view
everything else that comes with it you
know in a way I thought they would be
seeing yourself yourself as second
in the right way internally sure sure
but it's not a question of choice so if
I choose to put myself second it's just
acting out of your desire
yeah but yeah you can learn how to see
yourself second and then you won't be
able to take offense with anyone because
you always see yourself as this creature
over there it's not your problem not
yours
there's just I think that question also
sort of um
obviously it kind of shows the different
ways in which these two this like
protecting oneself is meant as in you
know when in a world of
greed and craving protecting oneself
naturally is assumed to mean okay okay
we're all at a table together and I'm
just gonna like grab all of the best
food for myself first and that's me
protecting myself because they say oh
you shouldn't do that
well yeah no that but that's obviously
not what is being meant here by
protecting oneself and then you know
and then so we should all share with one
another sure yeah that's better but in
in a sense what this is meaning is that
like you should protect yourself by
seeing Oh no okay is it I should just
not act out of desire and then for my
own benefit basically and then as a
secondary effect means that I don't
really I'm not gonna try and grab
everything to
yeah so you might then even still do
things like that somebody
with a different type of view might do
like for example being generous let's
say you could do that but you can do
that as a kind of a let me be generous
and show how much I'm giving and helping
yeah exactly so he has no wish for Heavens or
exactly so he has no wish for Heavens or
rewards of central benefits or something
but he's doing it for a completely
different reason that's invisible to
those without the Right View and that
reason is oh it it ornates my mind it's
the requisition adornment of my mind it
basically by by engaging in in
generosity towards
effortlessly this mind is embellished
beautifully and then I don't have to
bear bear it it's not difficult for me and
bear it it's not difficult for me and
it's not unpleasant to Bear it it's much
more much more easier to bear the mind
that's that's ornate and and uh and
light and embellished and wholesome so
he realized instead of
it's basically like the almost
recognizing the which is more efficient
effort to elevate your mind so that you
see it clearly and uh and exist with it
until it breaks apart more peacefully
so you can you can make this effort you
can make that effort but generosity oh
that takes very little yet the mind is
directly as a result of it embellished
and elevated
and he sees that directly and he does it
for that reason and no other
no no design for reward no desire for
thank you for that matter it doesn't
matter exactly absolutely it makes no
difference all he wants is his own mind to be
all he wants is his own mind to be
elevated on the result of it and in
protea without his benefit as well so
when you're if you're doing it for
somebody else now if they if they are
ungrateful or if they don't like it or
something I'm affected by that yeah so
you guys also I stopped doing it no no
you carry on doing it but now learn how
not to be affected by it
because there was exactly preceding was
you know they do it for the reward they
do it for the heavens uh and then to the
point of oh he just does it for the sake
of his own mind but it is factually good
generosity also but it's still worldly
married still partakes in the world in
the world in rebirth in samsara
so it's not the question of oh don't do
it because you can't do it purely you
won't be able to do it purely because
you're not anagami
you know the other hand
uh so do it whichever way you can and
then what comes as a result of it you
learn how not to be better in regard to
it whether it's the expectations of
heaven or being upset because you didn't
have enough thank you or gratitude
that's all secondary you keep doing it
and then you deal with these things on
the level of the Mind in a sense of
learn how not to be perturbed by those
things and then you will actually grow
and then you will actually grow
it says and how when safeguarding others
do you Safeguard yourself with yoniso
manisikara a mind of matter
a mind of matter
homelessness and patient endurance
hmm so it's all those internal practices
so it's all those internal practices
it's what we've been describing it
basically yeah
and there's just one more question even
when I know that my intentions are bad
or that my actions will lead to more
suffering I still don't stop cultivating
them therefore it seems that I don't really
therefore it seems that I don't really
care about myself
if I practice meta towards myself will I
be able to not choose bad actions next
time
putting the card in front of the horse
yeah practice the matter will not make you be
practice the matter will not make you be
able
to stop choosing badly not choosing
badly will enable you to stop choosing
badly and then you can practice matter
well in a way you're cultivating metal
yeah that's that's closer to price for
method than doing matter so that this is
dealt for me same people will know if I
get the Jannah the pleasure of Jannah
that's contemporarily taught then I will
just stop being attracted to Central
Pleasures but I won't have to go through
the Pains of withdrawal and overcoming
them I just need to get this so that
then this magically Falls away so if I
do meta my bad choices that I choose
will magically just stop happening
no yeah my decisions will change you
know so you want to do matter rightly
you start by not cultivating the choices
you already quite clearly quite well
understand you shouldn't be doing and
you don't care about yourself at the
time and that's correct you obviously
lose the context
so what do I do then well contemplate
the danger
peril obviously
obviously
sends restraint if you if you haven't
developed it
and then yeah the pattern will will be
too much to ignore
and then you will mix our choices to go
with it and this
and this
I thought I'd bring up this suit as well
because so how do you know what's good for you
so how do you know what's good for you
kind of thing
you most people they keep on doing bad
most people they keep on doing bad
things hmm
but if they knew that those were bad
things and they wouldn't do it hmm
but they in some way they think those
things are good you know it brings me
pleasure here and now later on but they
don't see the extent of how bad they are
oh yeah it's bad but no
but if they ever to see the extent of
the pedal the extent of the danger
then they would realize oh I cannot
engage with this
so and just to bring up The Suitor which
is how do you see that hmm
and it's uh the rahula one of the hula
suitors and the Buddha asks rahula what is a
and the Buddha asks rahula what is a
mirror for
eign answers for reflection
and the Buddha says in the same way same
way rahula bodily actions verbal actions
and mental actions are to be done with
repeated reflection or consideration
whenever you want to do a bodily
verbal mental Act
you should reflect on it
this act I want to do would it lead to
self-affliction to the Affliction of
others or to both would it be unskillful
would it be an unskillful action
resulting in dukkha
if on reflection you know that it would
lead to self-affliction to the
Affliction of others
or to both it would be an unskillful
bodily action resulting in Tuka then
endly body any action of that sort is
absolutely unfit for you to do
and the opposite is if you reflect
uh that these actions will not lead to
your self-affliction to another's
Affliction or to both it would be
skillful action resulting in happiness
then any action of that sort is fit for
you to do
and at the end he says rahula all those
contentatives in the past future present
and all who purified their bodily verbal
and mental actions did it to this
repeated reflection on their actions in
just this way no other way
so there is no magical thing you can do
they will then purify those things for
you in return yeah simply doesn't exist
when it exists is a wrong view yeah
but practically whoever has ever done it
successfully they did it through that
way as the Buddha himself as the Buddha
himself did purify his mind from the
unwholesome states how well when there
is a central loss present here we
establish the context of danger Peril
lack of satisfaction how not beneficial
for for him for other series and then
the thought would subside whenever it
subsides that was not his concern his
concern was to protect the context the
framework ill will thoughts of hatred context
ill will thoughts of hatred context
again of how little how little benefit
that has how it increases burden for you
and beneficial it is how friendliness is
much better option letting go is better
option how all these contexts he would
cultivate in face of these thoughts
and then they would subside eventually
keeps the context
endurance that we often talk about Kanti
forbearance patient endurance whichever
you want to translate it oh so you're
enduring the presence of this thought
which is pretty much the The Benchmark
for the context to be developed
until the thoughts of sides not until
you got rid of it
I got rid of what bothered me no you
were not bothered by it by trying to get
rid of it you bought it by your own
craving in regard to it
get rid of that but good luck getting
rid of that directly attending it or
replacing it impossible because you'll
be doing that with craving
but then you could do that with
like I said the the thought would
subside on its own but it's very easy to
fall into like I established the context
so that I got rid of this thought
because it's bothering me yeah yeah
exactly but so then what would be a
better intention that well to recognize
that you've been doing that and now
upgrade that as well establish the
context in regard to that you won't
start perfectly you will be wanting to
get rid of the pain yeah but by not
acting out that's already a better
context exactly regarding of the sensors
that's another better context by
contemplating the danger of sensuality
in face of sensuality even if you want
that centrality to go away well that's a
better context than just acting out like
before but now you really want to approve the
but now you really want to approve the
hindrances you have to recognize that
okay so I am doing this contemplation
now to get rid of this pain
and that whole thing is painful for me
now we can establish context in regards
to trying to get rid of pain
so how about then I start establishing
context that will prevent me they will
remove the attitude of trying to get rid
of it and actually establish the context
of worthwhile endurance
no just actually it is good to endure
these things I'm not acting out I'm not
proliferating I'm certainly not
welcoming them so now I shall patiently
endure them just because I know they
were never right
engage with it more I overstep and
activate my own craving in regard to it
so that's what I was gonna basically ask
yeah so a better intention than
let me establish the context to get rid
of this thought would be let me studies
let me establish this context so I can
endure this thought in its fullness
as
far as he wants to go without being
moved by it
and same for thoughts of ill will and
cruelty doubt doubt
as well